hey folks welcome to the Dark Horse
podcast livestream this is our tenth
livestream we're here we're phoning it
in just like you are get used to it
I'm sitting with dr. Heather huiying as
has become our way here on the Dark
Horse podcast and we are ready to talk
about developments over the last several
days relative to the Cova 19 situation
and much else let's see we had a couple
of announcements up front I'm not gonna
say housekeeping because for me that
always brings up an image of sam harris
and a french maids outfit for anyway so
and thank you for that yeah for everyone
listening thank you so we'll just say
maintenance or something maintenance
maintenance all right all right you well
yeah I guess we wanted to start by
saying as we did the end of the last Q&A
and we will try to do this at the end of
every of our live streams please if
you're enjoying this subscribe to the
channel like the video try notifications
share and and we are going to continue
to do what we've tried the last couple
of times the guard to the super chat
questions which is spend a little you
know by an hour doing this right now and
the super check questions coming in will
be logged we will then take about a 15
minute break between live streams and
we'll go through and just rank order
those questions mostly in terms of
monetary value but if anything jumps out
at us if we have time to see it that's
lower on the list we'll try to get to
that spend about a half an hour and the
next live stream the QA on that and then
we'll go in order received answering
questions in the next live stream from
super chat that comes in during that
live stream so that's the plan and
anything else yeah we had another
announcement which is that you and I are
doing a it would be called a lecture
coupled with an interrogation by
Professor Robby George at Princeton
that's right try to pull this up while
you're talking all right and this will
be this coming week on
Wednesday Tuesday it's gonna be I'm
trying to call this up as I'm talking to
you it's Wednesday April 29th at 4:30
p.m. Eastern Time so that's 1:30 p.m.
Pacific it's going to be done live and
the I think there's room for a thousand
registrants so I don't know what will
hit a thousand registrants but if you
want to regard is that if you want to
show the screen now oops
ah I must in order to watch it live you
do have to register but there's no fee
you don't have to be associated with
Princeton in any way here it is and and
it will be available later online
projects will be putting it up online so
if you miss it don't fret you'll be able
to find it and we will provide links on
our Twitter pages
the talk will involve a model of culture
and consciousness that we can promise
you you've never heard before and anyway
it should be very interesting so if that
is your style of thing please tune in
okay Zack you can drop it back to us
thank you all right
well I guess one other thing is that we
are going to save explicit Corrections
that really don't feed into the
conversation today until the end we're
gonna try that this time and so we're
just going to launch right into a
conversation here and then I've got a
couple Corrections that don't
necessarily relate to the rest of what
we're planning to talk about today that
we'll save for the end all right so I
wanted to start with to point to a
stunning success of yours from I believe
the last live stream well I like the
sound of this yes no it's good
you will no doubt have noticed that the
Santa Clara paper gets to live streams
the live streams together what paper
that you critiqued and if I recall your
position your position was I don't
necessarily this is I Heather do not
necessarily disagree with the conclusion
that this paper has reached I think it's
likely to be accurate but the
methodology is atrocious and here's why
and then you went on to point out that
the way they had solicited participants
in the study was obviously flawed and
just in several ways in which there
might be systematic bias let me
interrupt before you you go on the
conclusion of the study which I agree
with although I don't trust that this
paper I didn't trust that this paper had
actually gotten to these results
honestly was that background rates of
infection of SARS cough - are likely to
be much higher than we currently know
and if that's true that would lower the
mortality case fatality rate for SAR
scope do which would be good news and we
both think this is right based on the
fact that several studies have now
suggested that pattern however it
emerged we learned from Kiko in Boston a
longtime twitter friend of ours that the
study in question was revealed to have a
deep methodological flaw exactly where
you had suspected it would be and that
flaw was that the wife of the P ion the
study PII being the principal
investigator the main guy named a
money-getting guy yeah I had solicited
participants by emailing I think it was
an email list of parents of her kids
classmates or something like this it's
in private school but more importantly I
mean that is not in and of itself a bad
thing but what she had done was she had
said that they would get the
participants would get tested for free
with an fda-approved test that would
tell them whether or not they were safe
to return to work and so a the test is
not fda-approved and B this will tend to
bring in people who think they may well
have had it and may then get good news
which is you're immune and you can go
back to work and this is clearly going
to result in a bias in favor of people
who have had the disease or something
that might be it might look like it and
what's more it suggests that we know
something about immunity that we really
don't know which is what is the fate of
people who have had this does their
immunity lasts or does it decay and are
they again vulnerable down the road yeah
it wasn't just a blanket Facebook ad
which I had plenty of critique for
anyway but it was a as it turns out a
targeted send out at least in part of
that Facebook ad to people with the
such that if you think you might be
positive this could do you some good
so it it biased the subjects
participating in exactly the way that we
were concerned that I was concerned it
would it might buy it it might have been
biased this is the kind of thing that in
my experience he merges over the course
of years typically in here as a matter
of days but in any case very well done
this again not the paper right the paper
is not very well done spotting the flaw
it was very well done on your part and
this again points to a man behind the
curtain issue where the peer-reviewed
literature has some backstory that you
don't know can't see and because it's
gated we often don't find out what the
dirt is where the bodies are buried as
it were underneath studies like this so
later on in today's podcast we will talk
more about comparisons between the
peer-reviewed literature the archive the
archive literature which is not peer
reviewed but is still official in some
sense and a paper that doesn't appear in
either of those formats which is well
worth considering yeah I guess let me
say one thing this particular problem
with this paper is that you know the
wife of the principal investigator of
the paper went and basically solicited
subjects participants in the study in a
way that rendered the results not what
they would appear does actually remind
us of the value of human subjects review
and human subjects review boards which
are comp which are prevalent are exist
on every single campus and every single
I imagine research organization in which
human subjects are used which is a can
also to vertebrate animal committees
where if you're ever doing anything with
vertebrates you have to get permission
you have to you know walk through all of
what you're doing and basically get a
board of usually well board people who
don't really want to be doing the work
but who know that it's important that
before you say engage in research on
monkeys or engage in research on humans
that it passes the extant protocols for
for engaging and I imagine that if this
to go through Human Subjects review
which this work couldn't it's you know
it's it's too fast but one of one of the
benefits of the brakes on the system is
that human subjects were you would have
made it really really clear that such
such things wouldn't have been
appropriate that might not have stopped
it but it might it might at least have
revealed in say the dinner time
conversations between the dude and his
wife that you know this this actually is
not something you're allowed to do yeah
I hesitate to sign on to an embrace of
human subjects review because although I
believe there needs to be something that
does this job in practice it's so absurd
the way some things are granted I mean
if you want if you wanted to run a study
on a college campus where you stopped
people that you know in a public space
and asked them whether they remembered
their dreams from the prior night for
example you would need to go through
this process so and it has a there's a
just a bureaucratic element to it that's
insane but so at this is a complete
aside but another point against these
kinds of reviews vertebrate animal
review which you and I never worked on
people as graduate students but we've
both worked on vertebrate so we had to
go through some of the vertebrate animal
care committees at University of
Michigan where we did our graduate work
and you know these these forms are like
30 40 pages long they go on and on and
on and on and I was at that point
working on the sex lives of poison frogs
as one does and I wanted to bring back
tadpoles from I was working in the
Neotropics at that point Costa Rica or
Panama I don't remember which as I
wanted to bring back some adult frogs
and also do some work on tadpoles to see
if they would cannibalize each other at
different rates depending on their
degree of relatedness and so I had all
these justifications I've gotten some
grant money to do the work but I needed
or maybe I hadn't gotten the grant money
yet I had I had to get the vertebrate
animal protocols in place and when I got
the review back from the vertebrate
animal committee everything involving
tadpoles was struck out
and I thought no no and I got on the
phone with them I was like I was ready
to defend the work that I was going to
be doing and they talked me through and
I thought you know they thought very
patiently they figured they were dealing
with someone a little bit dim on the
other end of the phone and they
explained to me quite patiently that
while frogs are vertebrates tadpoles are
not in fact vertebrates and therefore I
did not need any permission to do
research on tadpoles I should point out
to any of our listeners who are tadpoles
you are vertebrates don't worry about
this it was a mistake on their part yeah
so I was able you know unfortunately for
people who might want to be doing on
unacceptable work the lesson was you can
do whatever you want as long as they're
young enough that the vertebrate animal
committee doesn't care so anyway these
committees are bureaucratic and they're
often flawed but but they they are set
up to do good work that doesn't mean
that they are doing good work all right
let's move on to a follow up not a
correction but a follow-up to a prior
discussion someone a listener to this
podcast alerted me in response to my
suggesting that military bases would be
good study populations to determine
questions like what is the damage to
people who've had asymptomatic cases of
Kovac 19 somebody said actually a recent
study was done on the cruise ship that
docked early in the pandemic in Japan
and in fact they were testing for
exactly that result so can you put that
up Zak so it's a study in radio and
radiology and cardiothoracic imaging and
it's chest CT findings in cases from a
cruise ship diamond princess with corona
virus disease 2019 okay so you can see
it now on your screen and can you scroll
a little bit I'm doing the scrolling so
where do you stop actually the abstracts
good enough okay so they tested a
hundred and four cases not a huge number
but enough to get the result and what
they found was something above half of
the asymptomatic cases that they looked
at
had these ground glass-like opacities in
the lung now I find this frightening and
fascinating how can it be that something
that is doing significant damage to the
lungs enough that it shows up on a CT
scan is asymptomatic from the point of
view of the person suffering the
condition maybe this is more common than
I know but that strikes me as very odd
in general even if you have difficulty
breathing as a result of a bad cold or
something if you don't have a pneumonia
you go to the doctor they look at your
lungs and they don't see very much so
maybe the CT scan is a bit different
than a standard x-ray it raises
questions about how homogenous how
homogeneous sensory neurons are across
humans and lungs alveolar function you
know all sorts of things how could you
have a lung CT that looks far different
and by all measures that we tend to use
far worse than it did two months earlier
and you feel no effect actually can you
scroll up we can see some of the a no-no
up the other way sorry you and I scroll
in different directions is one of the
places we don't get along all that well
keep going to the figures yes no no the
images there we go
so here you can see the arrows in this
image point to one of these ground-glass
opacities it's not the least bit subtle
and this one is from a 70 year old
asymptomatic woman all right so 70 year
old woman had severe damage to her lungs
during an infection in which she showed
no symptoms that is a fascinating and
frightening result yeah all right I
think that's enough there do you have
someplace you wanted to go next I
thought I think you're going to start us
off right okay so I wanted to call our
attention to something that another
twitter friend of ours alerted me to
just yesterday and I must say
this one caught me off guard I fell into
this here you're looking for the medium
piece yes
piece is on medium and it was written by
somebody who is there yeah okay yeah
okay it was written by I'm apologize if
I get your name wrong URI Deegan and URI
Deegan is not a biologist at least not
by training he is a life extension
person focused on epigenetic alterations
of cells so in general I don't get along
very well with the life extension people
because I think they're largely barking
up the wrong tree although if I had to
pick an area that was promising
epigenetic reset is probably highest on
the list or close to it in any case URI
has written an analysis of the Czar's
Cove to research and what it says about
the possibility that this pandemic was
triggered by a virus that is not in
effect natural now we should talk about
what that means but let me say up front
that he starts this piece by saying that
he was a skeptic and that he began to
dive into this research in the hopes of
arming himself so that he could properly
challenge and defeat claims that this
was a synthetic virus when he
encountered them and at some point he
says he was infected by the virus of
doubt now I read this hoping that I
would spot this term a no not at the
moment we can come back to it I read it
in the hopes of finding flaws in what he
said and not that the entire analysis
would necessarily be flawed but it would
be interesting if there was this
analysis in which he had come to believe
that there was a strong possibility of a
synthetic virus and it would be great to
have a counterpoint to that and I must
say I was a bit shocked by how thorough
he had been how careful he had been
and how compelling the overall analysis
was is very careful even in the
conclusion he says this doesn't nail
anything down but what it does is mean
that the possibility is live so let me
say a bit about what it would mean for
this to be a synthetic virus it does not
mean that somebody invented it it would
mean that it is a chimera of pieces from
different viruses that had been created
by natural selection and that chimera
would have an increased capacity to
infect people on the basis of having you
know the molecular machinery from this
virus over here that facilitates binding
to the surface of a human cell and
molecular machinery from over here that
facilitates cleaving a particular
protein that would make it more likely
to invade the cell so in any case I want
to point out that this is the
counterpoint here on medium a not very
widely read post at this point is
challenging a paper that was published
in Nature that we covered in an earlier
livestream and the paper in nature said
there's almost no chance that this is a
synthetic virus and made several
arguments oh well a lot of their
argument which I objected to at the time
was that it didn't look to them like it
was engineered because it wasn't the
people engineering it would have made
choices that didn't seem like the right
choices not that it wasn't possible to
have made those choices but there was
inference about the the choices made by
the would be engineers rather than an
argument that it wasn't possibly
engineered so this raises a number of
questions one is what would it be
engineered for and I want to make very
clear that the idea that this virus was
engineered in a lab is not synonymous
with the idea that this is a bio weapon
it could be one of the the reasons you
might engineer a virus in a lab would be
to use it in an offensive way but there
are plenty of other reasons to engineer
a virus in the lab and in fact
one of the things that this paper does
so beautifully is it reveals what this
very small network of laboratories that
are studying that coronaviruses is
actually doing and one thing that I
think is quite clear from this analysis
is that there is an incredibly dangerous
subfield building viruses routinely in
the lab with gain-of-function chimerism
that is to say where they borrow
function from one virus put it in
another and then infect cells of one
type or another that's right
so these gain-of-function research
protocols create novel viruses that do
not exist in nature and there is always
the chance that one of these things will
escape now did that happen in this case
we don't know but the fact of one of the
two primary labs involved in this
research it's not that these labs are
all over the place there are really two
primary labs studying bat corona viruses
and their potential threat to human
health one of these labs is in Wuhan
China so the coincidence of this virus
having emerged there and the story that
it is connected to a so-called wet
market when in fact the the indications
that it came from the wet market are
quite insecure there were early cases
numerous early cases more cases than
were connected to the wet market that
had no connection to it that anyone
could find at all and so there is a
small number of scientists engaged in
finding novel viruses by collecting bats
from other parts of China abstracting
their viruses and then tinkering by
playing around with their molecular
machine
and the level of danger there would be
hard to overstate yeah so I guess a
number of things just to add into the
mix here Zach if you want to put up the
screen here we have another preprint
server paper that is to say not not yet
peer-reviewed but written as if the goal
is for it to be peer-reviewed this is
actually from over a month ago now March
19th 2020 evidence of the recombinant
origin and ongoing mutations and severe
acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus
two sorries co2 and these these authors
argue that there is it's the spike
protein on the surface of the virus that
appears to be Pangolin in origin and it
is the rest of the virus that appears to
be bat in origin and so they're using
this this word recombinant not to
presume that it was human recombination
not in the way of saying recombinant
tomato which has a fish gene inserted
into it to make it more freeze resistant
as in the style of various GMOs but that
this that this would have happened
naturally right and you know we have to
be careful with this word natural of
course but when we're using it here we
mean is we mean not in a lab not by
human directed research what it what it
leaves open though is well how did and
we've talked about this a little bit in
previous live streams how exactly did
this particular bat where this virus is
understood to be transmitted a virus to
a Pangolin in the first place and then
how did the Pangolin transmit that to
humans and you know we have explored ok
yes people do eat Pangolin sometimes but
it's actually the pet the bat Pingel in
connection which is one of the most
difficult ones to understand at an
ecological level whereas and maybe ok so
i take it down for a minute while i find
here we have yeah you can put this up
now Zak so this is the site for the
National Center for biodiversity
information NCBI
and it's a clearinghouse for taxonomy
it's not just viruses we'll show you in
a little bit
a really good site that is was created
by some bioinformatics people to
specifically track emerging pathogens
but this is a site that is used across
the taxonomic world across all organisms
on earth as a as a place to go to find
to find genomes and such so here you
have the lineage of this is a you know
not very exciting page as is the way
with both government and taxonomic sites
generally but this lineage basically
reads left to right where the leftmost
thing virus is is the most inclusive and
everything to the right of that you know
if if if ripe of area are viruses then
so are Corona Tevere na and so is
everything to the right at this right so
we have here this particular species
severe acute respiratory syndrome
related corona viruses but even that is
a category right so if I click on that
look at all of the SARS related corona
viruses it goes on and on and on and on
there are a tremendous number of them
and so you know how many of these were
in fact created in a lab versus were
created organically out there in the
world when organisms came into contact
with one another some of them are
creations almost certainly and some of
them some of them are not and you know
for for legitimately lab-created viruses
presumably much of that information is
out there now somewhere on here we have
I can't find it's just too much here we
have you know civet viruses and Pangolin
viruses and lots and lots and lots of
bat viruses so take it back off sack
while I find one more so can we can we
talk a little about these ecological
question this is one of the things that
I think is most important we have two
lines of inquiry developing one has to
do with how this virus functions and how
we're going to defeat it and then
there's another question about where it
came from and what that implies in other
words if somebody released a bioweapon
that obviously calls for one kind of
response if it was an accidental release
from a lab it's another kind of response
we actually need to know the answer to
this question yeah and if you think
about the fact that there are a couple
of primary labs that are doing this work
of creating novel viruses whether they
were involved or not we need what they
know
we need that expertise and at the moment
Zhi Jing Li who is the head of the lab
in Wuhan that does this work is
experiencing a situation in which there
is wild speculation on the internet
about what her involvement was can you
put up the the is a Scientific American
paper that is coming out I believe in
their June if you oh you don't have it I
don't know all right
Scientific American is going to can
search but I mean this no I'm sorry
hired for this it's all right sure it is
a paper that they put out basically a a
profile of Jiujiang Li which describes
her laboratories work and concludes that
we know that her laboratory was not
involved in having created this thing so
what the function of that article is is
a little hard to say but again the
coincidence here is spectacular let me
yeah that's the one
all right Zack is gonna put this up and
we will put links to this in the
description okay so we can yeah
okay good so how China's Batwoman hunted
down viruses from SARS to the new corona
virus and the virus that bears the most
resemblance to the currently circulating
human coronavirus is from Yunnan
Province in I believe southwestern China
and there is interesting discussion in
the paper on medium about the fact that
that sample that is closest to the human
circulating virus was apparently
collected in 2013 by the Jing Li and
again I apologize if I'm getting your
name wrong there's angley lab though
they did not publish on it at the time
they revealed in the present that this
was the closest sequence and it is
anomalously close in almost all regards
except the spiked protein where it has
this Pangolin sequence and so you raised
the right point which is is there an
ecological my computer so I can find
something I'll show you guys is there an
ecological path for a recombination
event to have taken the Pangolin spike
protein and put it into this this virus
from a rhino low fat bat or not now I
can't say one way or the other what I
can say from the years of work I did as
a bat researcher is that I bet the
number of people who have expertise on
relevant bats is very very small we need
to know who they are and we need to talk
to them about what the ecology of these
animals is there's not very much
available but some graduate students
somewhere may have studied these animals
and we can know something about whether
or not pangolins and these bats ever
encounter encounter each other because
what would have to take place for that
recombination event I believe somebody
should correct me if I've got it wrong
but the only mechanism I can see for a
recombination event is that an
individual animal either bad or Pangolin
presumably bad since that would be the
more likely route for it to get back out
to humans would have to be infected with
two corona viruses and those two viruses
would have to invade the same cell in
order for there to be genetic exchange
that's a very unlikely my tilt in order
to get so you've got the spiked protein
from one from the Pangolin and you've
got the rest of the genome from the bat
some animal has to have both in order
for nature to have recombined these
things so in essence I guess the
proposal in the paper though is that a
bat infected a Penguin's the Pangolin
has the virus that it has and the bat
infects the Pangolin with whatever the
pyrite bat has so there's there's it has
to be some of this be simultaneously be
a reservoir for to foreign viruses in
order if you're that Pangolin which you
know we're sort of raising questions
about whether or not that really makes
sense as an ecological and would have
transferred but you just have to be a
bat that's infected that somehow
transfers your virus into the Pangolin
and you know and then the recombination
happens by right you know that's a
that's a big black box right there but
just being sick with the two viruses is
not likely to do it they have to end up
in the same cell which may be very
likely depending upon how widespread it
is in the body but my point is somehow
it will not necessarily be very valuable
with respect to figuring out what to do
about this virus circulating in the
human population but in terms of
figuring out what it is and how this
happened and how it can never happen
again and is somebody responsible in a
way that needs to be addressed we have
to gather people with various different
kinds of expertise so I find I'm now
struggling I have two kinds of expertise
relevant to this story just by accident
one of them is phylogenetic systematics
and one of them is bats so far the genic
systematics for those people who don't
know what that means which is to say all
but probably two of the people watching
right now just refers to the science of
figuring out who was related to whom it
is not the science of naming organisms
which is taxonomy but it is figuring out
once you have a bunch of organisms what
the history of relationships was and so
in some sense phylogenetic systematics
almost never comes up in the news but at
the moment it's news why because when
you try to draw a phylogeny
of these viruses you don't get a clear
signal why because part of it is coming
from Pangolin and part of it is coming
from bat so that could be the result of
a natural
fact or it could be the result of an
artificial fact and before you you go to
that let me just say so I can say
something about bats I can say something
about phylogenetic systematics
I'm not a virologist I'm not an
epidemiologist and I'm not a molecular
biologist right now I would say at least
you want those five kinds of expertise
in order to navigate a question about
could this have come from nature so the
three things again are bat biology which
you have and I have a little bit but
mostly through you phylogenetic
systematics which we both have in which
we know to be pretty rare even among
biologists it's considered kind of niche
and you have to have ended up in the
right place with the right people to end
up with with deep understanding of it
you have said biology epidemiology and
what was your fifth that that we are not
expert in biology epidemiology and
molecular biology okay especially
molecular techniques so what I think you
want is a roomful of people you know it
doesn't have to be a lot of people but
there has to be some expertise on all of
these things and you know for me to say
I'm a bat biologist I have almost no
experience with Ryan LOF at bats I have
captured them on a couple of occasions
when I've done some work in the old
world but my bad expertise doesn't buy
me very much except that I know that
these animals are likely to be found in
caves that those caves might have
multiple species in them not necessarily
from the same family so there's a
pipistrelle bat that also shows up to
have a tiny sequence homology to the
circulating human virus that's an
entirely different family could they be
roosting together they very definitely
could be but in any case the Pangolin
experts we need to talk to them the bad
experts especially the Rhino low-fat
experts we need to talk to them we need
to put them in contact with the viola
gist's and the molecular biologists in
order to have a conversation about what
could possibly explain what we are
seeing yeah especially given this sack
would you put this up coming out of
nature a week a little more than a week
ago China is tightening its grip on
coronavirus research
and some scientists are saying no this
is good we need the research coming out
of China to be to be accurate but it
looks to many of us like an attempt to
control information right so if papers
that were up even on these pre print
servers are being pulled and basically
here's the first paragraph it's just
it's a news article in nature it's not a
research article over the past two
months China's government appears to
have quietly introduced policies that
require scientists to get approval to
publish or publicize their results
according to documents seen by nature
and some researchers this means as we
have alluded to in the past that
regardless of which of the three main
hypotheses for the origin of this virus
is true it is completely organic and
emerged out of a wet market it was
engineered and was being engineered in
pursuit of better understanding these
viruses so that public human public
health globally could be improved or it
was engineered and it was being
engineered for the purpose of bio weapon
regardless of which of those three
hypotheses is actually true and we are
both you and I are both leading strongly
turns that middle one but there was some
engineering going on but that it wasn't
for nefarious purposes regardless of why
if China is obscuring research and
keeping people from talking then we
cannot simply trust what China is
telling us and we need smart people in a
realm with a relevant background and
ability to troubleshoot and
problem-solve and say oh I hadn't
thought of that and I was wrong about
this and oh holy hell what if and you'll
be allowed to hypothesize in ways that
might seem extraordinary without those
hypotheses coming back to haunt them
because they were wrong absolutely I
would also say I'm very dismayed as you
point out about the way China has
behaved controlling information false
influenza this is extremely destructive
dangerous behavior that's certainly
costing lives on the other hand one of
the things that this this medium post
alerted me to was just how international
this effort to study these
Korona viruses is and so yes the
laboratory in question is in Wuhan China
the NIH gave a grant to study this so
the National Institutes of Health which
is the main funder American United
States funder of medical research right
and the main competitor laboratories in
the US Ralph
barukh I think is the name of the p i--
in that lab and they sort of trade back
and forth one-upping each other in terms
of their sophistication at modifying
coronaviruses and so anyway this is
something you could be pretty well
unaware of and then suddenly virus
emerges in Wuhan and we're all grappling
with oh there happens to be a lab there
what does that mean oh they were
studying that coronaviruses and the one
with the greatest analogy to the
circulating virus happens to have been
one they collected in 2013 and didn't
publish about so all of these things are
potentially connected also the case that
it turns out to the reason that we know
that there is an analogy of the spy
protein to the Pangolin virus is that a
number of pangolins were confiscated
they were being smuggled in China they
died in captivity at a rehab center from
coronavirus symptoms
swabs were taken sent to labs where do
we think they went they may very well
have ended up in these labs who may very
well have spotted a spike protein whose
function they wanted to investigate and
if you look at the publication history
of these labs swapping these components
out and seeing what the resultant virus
can do is just standard practice so
could this virus have been created as a
result of just basic research it could
have and and which you know we don't
know if that's what happened but it
points to the potential not the
guaranteed but the potential danger of
doing recombinant Engineering an
organism such as what GMOs are right it
points to the potential for great danger
far greater than what we are hoping no
one intended in this case
and certainly no one intends when
they're trying to make save crops less
susceptible to pests and such yep I
would also point out that the danger of
skullduggery here is also spectacular I
still believe that this virus is an odd
one to have created if your intent was
to release it into the world to cause
havoc mmm
on the other hand let's say that
somebody and again one of the points
from the medium article is that the
technology to swap components of the
virus is now within reach of a graduate
student at the level you know who's
studying these viruses and so that's a
that's a pretty large number of people
who might have the the laboratory
capacity to do this sort of work let's
say that somebody decided to wreak havoc
well if they were gonna release the
thing for the purpose and you know I
would just come up with a placeholder
for a purpose if somebody let's say
somebody sociopathic enough not to care
that they were gonna cause a lot of
death but interested in making some
money wanted to short a bunch of markets
knowing that havoc on earth would lead
to markets collapsing where would they
release it so as not to have their
fingerprints on it well probably they
would release it somewhere where it
would be traced back to some laboratory
that might not have been involved so we
have to be really careful just because
the connection between this virality lab
in Wuhan and the viruses they studied
and this virus that is now traversing
the globe seems to paint a very clear
picture of course the problem is that
very clear picture could be real or it
could be what somebody wants us to see
for their own purposes and we because we
don't know their purpose can't infer it
from what has been released yep okay
should we talk a little bit about the
diversity in the virus which is to say
we have well actually
excuse me exactly when to put up this
screen this is from a different site not
NCBI the last site we were talking about
was the National Center for biodiversity
information
which is a federal site this is an
organization actually I'm going to just
flip the screen for a moment this is an
organization that was written about and
a peer-reviewed paper in 2018 which is
private and it aims to do real-time
tracking the pathogen evolution and so
these are bioinformatics people not
necessarily phylogenetic systematics and
so you know it's really hard to to know
and also assess the various
methodologies here and probably this is
not the place to go into the various
methodological problems with a number of
the approaches and systematics but take
a look at this at this on the left here
this is you know unlike classic
cladogram on the horizontal loops on the
horizontal axis here we actually have
time because each time a genome was
collected from an infected person a
viral genome was collected from an
infected person we know exactly when
that happened and so time is on the I
want to say x-axis but it's not the
x-axis and and you have beginning in
December early December going all the
way to this is a sort of mid-april and
what these authors the site has done is
basically color coded change the color
of the viral genomes every time there is
sufficient change for it to feel like
it's a different strain to them now this
is obviously a judgment call we got a
question last livestream with a link to
an article that said oh there's 30
strains now and that article turned out
to be very frustrating because none of
the links were to actual research they
were always two more articles within
that same not particularly valuable
newspaper and there was no way to figure
out from the article what research it
was referencing actually but are there
30 strains or they're eight strands or
800 strains are there as many strains as
there are people who are infected it's
something something in there right so as
I think you said last time Brett I mean
I think I think you said just this that
there are by some by some counts
as many strands as there are as there
are infection moments right well the
problem is it that's not even the upper
bound you could have multiple strains in
an individual depending upon mutation
rate I think the mutation rate here is
not high enough that we're liable to
have a number as large as the number of
infected people or greater but my
complaint the last time was that thirty
strains might be the number of strains
that have gotten a toehold in the world
and moved forward so because the world
is editing down these strains to the
very rare more successful ones that's
what we see it doesn't mean that there
aren't innumerably many strains
circulating somewhere at this point
right so sorry that keeps I'm having a
hard time with this track bad we can
look at the same information in a
different view a radial view which I
often find very confusing but in this
case the middle of the circle is the
beginning of time for this virus which
again on this is December 3rd 2019 and
and it's also a spatial it's it's
spatial representation so again you see
in purple the original virus coming out
of command of China and then pretty
quickly mutating into a number of
different strains which again these
authors have have color cording
color-coded so let even play the sheriff
of this animation Brett why not um just
a very hard time making this work okay
unfortunately I can't make that
fullscreen so the animation on the right
is the map showing it's spread out of
China and you have the comparable move
in the radial phylogram on the left of
how it is moving in the in the tree that
was created so also the changes in color
on the map on the right are what are
being counted as new strains that are
emerging spreading the dots are the
spread within a country
and then the lines are transmissions
that are inferred between countries
exactly the size of the dot is relative
caseload is according to you know what's
being reported which of course we as
we've talked about many many times that
information is is very incomplete and I
want to say too that you know that what
are we going backwards now okay the
distinction between strains is somewhat
arbitrary and certainly is not going to
be judged the same way by every person
looking at them just like the
distinction between species is not a
hard-and-fast line so complex systems
complex categories tend to have fuzzy
boundaries between them and the idea
that we can count exactly eight or
exactly 30 or exactly some number of
strains is asking a bit much for a
rapidly evolving RNA virus yeah I don't
think we need to know I think it is
worth understanding that this thing and
we should expect us having just met the
human population it is liable to be a
poor match in many ways
and rapid evolution is what you expect
because you have innumerable individual
copies in each person who's infected you
have large numbers of infected people
and any discovery any mutation that
results in greater transmission will
obviously show up as an ancestor to some
large new clade of the stuff so we
should expect to see that here and and
we are seeing it I think you can take it
down now Zack Thanks so what is your
takeaway about the discovery that there
is apparently a very rapid small
sociological cluster of people
augmenting the function of coronaviruses
found in nature for the purpose
ostensibly of figuring out how to
prevent them from escaping and killing
people
so sociological cluster meaning small
number of people who go to the same
conferences and read each other's papers
and one-up each other and that sort of
thing yeah it's not surprising at all is
it I mean I of course and we can all act
surprised that we didn't know about this
particular thing before now but this is
the risk that has come to meet us
and there are presumably many others
with many other clusters of researchers
working on dangerous things that you
know the work itself being risky does
not mean it shouldn't be done but what
kind of oversight you know if this was
engineered and accidental release what
kind of oversight could have been in
place to prevent the release is it in
fact possible is it in fact possible in
a globalized world where you have
researchers from at least two of the
world's major superpowers and presumably
more than that actively involved in the
research with their own not just
political differences because of the
governments that live under but also
presumably personality differences you
know just two people - two individual
labs within a university are gonna have
differences much less between
universities much less between
universities and nations well I have to
say I am disturbed it's not that this
was unknown obviously it was in the
literature and there was a certain
amount of pushback in 2015 over a paper
that was published in nature which
revealed some of what was going on and
alarmed a number of people but it
there's an obvious question about the
value of this research in preventing
future hazards and the danger that it
will cause one of these hazards to
emerge
obviously shutting down official
research does not prevent people from
doing this privately off label so the
danger may exist irrespective of what
the official position is but I'm shocked
at the discovery that this
gain-of-function research is absolutely
commonplace working with viruses
are absolutely known to be potential
emergent hazards and you asked what kind
of safeguards could you put in place the
only good one I can think of is maybe if
this research needs to be done it needs
to be done on hips and there needs to be
some protocol where the work is done at
some point the samples are destroyed it
doesn't dock for two weeks you know I
don't know what the right protocol would
be but I don't like the sense and in
fact this reminds me of something I have
thought each time we've had one of these
major emergent disasters of late right
we had Fukushima we had the Deepwater
Horizon we had Aliso Canyon in Los
Angeles right even have to spell that
one out for most viewers I think well
that was a release of gases from a mine
that had been used as a natural gas
storage facility so some large cavern
underground had been that had had
natural gas pumped into it and it sprung
a leak that was poisoning people in the
local neighborhood and was unplug Abul
in the same way that the Deepwater
Horizon leak was unplug alone so anyway
each time one of these things have so
you should also put on the list the
financial collapse of 2008 where we
discovered the degree of leveraging and
all of this each time one of these
things happen I have the sense of okay
it took the disaster for me to find out
what it was that somebody needed to tell
me was happening right I needed to know
that mortgage-backed securities were
being played with in this particular way
in order to understand how much risk we
were at I needed to know about you know
fuel pools and spent fuel in nuclear
reactors and the possibility of a you
know prompt criticality causing one of
these pools to bust before Fukushima I
find out after well this is part of what
long-form investigative journalism is
for
and we've seen a decline in long-form
investigative journalism with the change
in the in basically the financial model
for journalism where it's about clicks
and very short term attention spans and
it's hard to get funding to send someone
to do what maybe a six or nine month
research project and result in you know
10 minute documentary or a five thousand
word think piece this is true but it is
also you know as Eric has been
repeatedly raising there's a question
about what could possibly explain the
level of dysfunction in investigative
journalism it's hard to account for and
so what I want to know discovering that
this what looks to me like an extremely
well researched reasoned and careful
article on medium describing the
scenario that might have unfolded
explaining our current global pandemic
mm-hmm that that piece has cleared none
of the hurdles right this is just
something somebody decided to write and
publish for their own purposes now the
question is given that head start
is that going to get picked up by any
major publication well so let me also
point to long before that well I don't
know long but before that medium piece
came out that medium piece is just the
last day or two I think a few days
before that actually no we have this as
ii put this up now this is on github
this is version 7.6 this is an ongoing I
think it's basically a wiki document
between among many many authors and
everything is public here the title
being evidence that's our scope to
emerge from a Biological Laboratory in
Wuhan China and they just they do an
incredibly careful job of spelling out
absolutely everything that they assume
everything they think they know
everything and you know including you
know here's the section on if we're
right what it means if we're wrong
either way what doesn't change something
on nomenclature you know why we call it
or what we're calling these things and
then finally sorry I'm going to go back
up to the top and
say if you'd like to see a summarized
version of every claim in this document
please see the conclusion and my god
it's really really careful it's it's
remarkable and you know this this right
here is investigative journalism that's
not what these guys are calling
themselves but that's what this is so a
finder it's very similar in some ways to
the medium piece that you begin the show
talking about except this is effectively
a group effort and we're on version I
think it says the seven point six so
there's a lot of iterations if this is
github then it's an open source
collaborative project this is an
entirely different mechanism for doing
journalism the medium piece is one
person's incredible effort to summarize
material this is a different way of
doing it but think of the comparison
here at the same point that this widely
reported study in in Santa Clara County
is having to be corrected because of an
obvious methodological flaw that NEP I
should have understood was a no it was a
completely unacceptable method right
what is it that fosters that kind of
spectacular error being published in a
highly regarded Journal and being widely
reported by the world's newspapers right
at the same time that we have authors
collaborating on this high-quality work
on github and we have other people doing
the work on medium I mean to me this is
really the it's the vindication for
those of us who have believed that peer
review was the problem not the solution
and it actually provides a reason for
optimism believe it or not you know that
that this kind of this quality of work
both this github piece and the medium
piece are out there now and are getting
some attention and
garnering careful critique and being
spread around is is exactly as you say
something of it's not even a consolation
prize it's you know what isn't isn't
this some evidence that peer review was
in fact at least part of the problem and
what's more for anybody who would say no
we need peer review to keep the junk out
well there it is it's on the internet
you can find it too if you are a
highly-placed individual and you think
this stuff is nonsense let's hear why
let's expose that out in the open rather
than behind closed doors where you
usually shut work like this down all
right all right I just had one thing I
wanted to say as a as a correction from
last time unless there's more that you
want to say before before we switch
gears yeah all right
so in the last Q&A we were talking about
food I think someone asked about the
role of sugar and the diet the clear
implication the question being we now
well understood that sugar is a poison
effectively and I as part of my answer
said absolutely and we tend to eat real
sugars and then I mentioned fructose and
that's you know not not a particularly
healthy sugar molecule in fact all that
I'm gonna pull up not yet Zack this is
for those who are interested in seeing
Zack if you want to now show the screen
it's a 2009 article which specifically
looked at the effects of fructose versus
glucose sweetened beverages on people
who were otherwise healthy but somewhat
overweight they had these people
increase their caloric intake every day
by 500 more calories of pure fruit as
importantly your glucose it's kind of
appalling actually that they the human
subject review let these people do this
research but they found except for
actual weight gain all the other
measures of health were much worse
pure glucose of pure fructose increased
vs. up here and glucose increase so you
can take that down as AG so that's true
that glucose is in fact you know if
you're going to pick your sugars the
molecular level it would be better to
choose glucose over fructose but it's
also interesting to see that my you know
brief ill-advised foray into production
ISM which I don't tend to engage in
prompted a number of people to spell out
exactly why particular molecules were
better for you than others and this is
actually exactly antithetical to what
the kind of answer I was trying to give
and what you know what the message that
I was trying to provide which was many
people have far too much faith in this
modern mindset that sounds like science
but it's actually scientism that sounds
like big emergent theory but is actually
production ISM you know it's data-driven
rather than hypothesis driven and
breaking things into their component
parts and then assuming that you've
found all the component parts and you
can accurately count them and that none
of them are contingent on any of the
others is in fact part of the problem so
sugar is clearly pretty clearly a
dietary toxin but eating maple syrup
even honey
eating sugars that armor in eating fruit
in moderation is far far better for you
that eating those sugars that have been
parsed out and turned into their
constituent parts and then pieced back
together for you and created you know
provided for you in an easy form so that
you can make them and you end up with a
nice sheen on your cake or something you
know I as I said before like I do that I
bake I enjoy doing it but the the sugars
that are more holistically emerging from
the plants from which they came are
going to be healthier alternatives all
right all right so we'll return in 15
minutes yep so subscribe yes yes uh we
would like you to subscribe hit like hit
notify and spread the word that would be
very useful to us and we appreciate it
we will see you in about
fifteen minutes there will be a link in
the description to this video to the QA
section and you can start adding super
check questions now excellent see you
there